{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Mass transfer rate between two fluid phases does not necessarily depend on the __________ of the two phases.", "opta": "chemical properties", "optb": "physical properties", "optc": "degree of turbulence", "optd": "interfacial area", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a solution containing 0.30 Kg mole of solute and 600 kg of solvent, the molality is", "opta": "0.50", "optb": "0.60", "optc": "2", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fenske equation determines the", "opta": "maximum number of ideal plates.", "optb": "height of the distillation column.", "optc": "minimum number of theoretical plates.", "optd": "optimum reflux ratio.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The term \"cooling range\" in a cooling tower refers to the difference in the temperature of", "opta": "cold water leaving the tower and the wet bulb temperature of the surrounding air.", "optb": "hot water entering the tower and the wet bulb temperature of the surrounding air.", "optc": "hot water entering the tower and the cooled water leaving the tower.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for extraction in a system having very low density difference ?", "opta": "Mixer-settler extractor", "optb": "Centrifugal extractor", "optc": "Pulsed extractor", "optd": "Packed extraction tower", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Total reflux in a distillation operation requires minimum", "opta": "reboiler load", "optb": "number of plates", "optc": "condenser load", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of steam required per unit quantity of distillate in case of steam distillation will be reduced by", "opta": "raising the temperature.", "optb": "lowering the total pressure.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference of wet bulb temperature and adiabatic saturation temperature of unsaturated mixture of any system is", "opta": "+ve", "optb": "-ve", "optc": "zero", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fenske's equation for determining the minimum number of theoretical stages in distillation column holds good, when the", "opta": "relative volatility is reasonably constant.", "optb": "mixture (to be separated) shows negative deviation from ideality.", "optc": "mixture (to be separated) shows positive deviation from ideality.", "optd": "multicomponent distillation is involved.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the temperature and humidity of air is low, we usually use __________ draft cooling tower.", "opta": "natural", "optb": "forced", "optc": "induced", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "In case of liquid-liquid extraction, no separation is possible, if the selectivity of the solvent used is unity.", "optb": "With increase in temperature, the selectivity of the solvent used in solvent extraction decreases.", "optc": "The selectivity of solvent used in solvent extraction is unity at the plait point.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ columns are used for liquid dispersion in a continuous gas phase.", "opta": "Packed", "optb": "Pulse", "optc": "Bubble cap", "optd": "Sieve plate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Overall efficiency of the distillation column is", "opta": "the ratio of number of ideal plates to actual plates.", "optb": "the ratio of number of actual plates to ideal plates.", "optc": "same as the Murphree efficiency.", "optd": "always more than the point efficiency.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On addition of solute in the solvent, the __________ of the solution decreases.", "opta": "boiling point", "optb": "freezing point", "optc": "vapour pressure", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the controlling factor for a drum drier?", "opta": "Diffusion", "optb": "Heat transfer", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Drying operation under vacuum is carried out to", "opta": "dry those materials which have very high unbound mositure content.", "optb": "reduce drying temperature.", "optc": "increase drying temperature.", "optd": "dry materials having high bound moisture content.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Air initially at 101. 3 kPa and 40\u00b0C and with a relative humidity of 50%, is cooled at constant pressure to 30\u00b0C. The cooled air has a", "opta": "higher dew point.", "optb": "higher absolute (specific) humidity.", "optc": "higher relative humidity", "optd": "higher wet bulb temperature.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Separation of two or more components of a liquid solution can not be achieved by", "opta": "fractional crystallisation", "optb": "liquid extraction", "optc": "absorption", "optd": "evaporation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stefan's law describes the mass transfer by", "opta": "diffusion", "optb": "bulk flow", "optc": "both 'a' & 'b'", "optd": "neither 'a' nor 'b'", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At minimum reflux ratio for a given separation", "opta": "number of plates is zero.", "optb": "number of plates is infinity.", "optc": "minimum number of the theoretical plates is required.", "optd": "separation is most efficient.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Relative humidity is the ratio of the", "opta": "partial pressure of the vapour to the vapour pressure of the liquid at room temperature.", "optb": "partial pressure of the vapour to the vapour pressure of the liquid at gas temperature.", "optc": "actual humidity to saturation humidity.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In batch distillation with constant reflux, overhead product composition __________ with time.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "does not vary", "optd": "may increase on decrease, depends on the system.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Psychrometry deals with the properties of gas-vapor mixture. Humidity can be determined by the measurement of the __________ of a fibre.", "opta": "electrical resistance", "optb": "thermal conductivity", "optc": "strength", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat in BTU necessary to increase the temperature of 1 lb of gas and its accompanying vapour by 1\u00b0F is called the", "opta": "latent heat", "optb": "humid heat", "optc": "specific heat", "optd": "sensible heat", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To increase the absorption factor, (where, G = gas flow rate, S = solvent flow rate)", "opta": "increase both 'G' and 'S'.", "optb": "decrease both 'G' and 'S'.", "optc": "increase 'S' and decrease 'G'.", "optd": "increase 'G' and decrease 'S'", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mass diffusivity, the thermal diffusivity and the eddy momentum diffusivity are same for, NPr = NSc = __________", "opta": "1", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "10", "optd": "0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dew point of a gas-vapour mixture", "opta": "increases with temperature rise.", "optb": "decreases with temperature rise.", "optc": "decreases with decrease in pressure.", "optd": "increases with increase in pressure.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a packed absorption tower, if the equilibrium and operating lines are both straight lines, then the ratio, HETP/HTUOG __________ the absorption factor.", "opta": "increases with increase in", "optb": "is one at unity value of", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following plays an important role in problems of simultaneous heat and mass transfer ?", "opta": "Lewis number", "optb": "Schmidt number", "optc": "Prandtl number", "optd": "Sherwood number", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of an absorber, the operating", "opta": "line always lies above the equilibrium curve.", "optb": "line always lies below the equilibrium curve.", "optc": "line can be either above or below the equilibrium curve.", "optd": "velocity is more than the loading velocity.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As the reflux ratio in a distillation coloumn is increased from the minimum, the", "opta": "slope of the operating line in stripping section decreases.", "optb": "number of plates decreases very slowly first and then more and more rapidly.", "optc": "total cost first decreases and then increases.", "optd": "liquid flow increases while the vapor flow decreases for a system.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absorption factor is defined as (where, S1 = slope of the operating line S2 = slope of the equilibrium curve)", "opta": "S2/S1", "optb": "S1/S2", "optc": "S1 - S2", "optd": "S1 x S2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A plait point is the point on the solubility curve, where the tie line reduces to a point. What is the number of plait point for a ternery system containing twopairs of partially miscible liquids ?", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following remains constant during sensible cooling process ?", "opta": "Specific humidity", "optb": "Partial pressure of vapour", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Physical absorption is", "opta": "an irreversible phenomenon.", "optb": "a reversible phenomenon.", "optc": "accompanied by evolution of heat.", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Make up water is required in a cooling tower to replace the water lost by", "opta": "evaporation", "optb": "drift", "optc": "blowdown and leakage", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following quantities need not be fixed before starting the design of a co-current absorber ?", "opta": "Heat gain or loss", "optb": "Flow rate of entering liquid", "optc": "Flow rate of gas", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mass transfer co-efficient of liquid is", "opta": "affected more by temperature than that for gases.", "optb": "affected much less by temperature than that for gases.", "optc": "not affected by the temperature.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absorption accompanied with chemical reaction is exemplified by the absorption of", "opta": "ammonia in water.", "optb": "benzol present in coke oven gas by wash oil.", "optc": "SO2 in alkaline solution.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following unit operations makes use of Thiele-Geddes equation ?", "opta": "Liquid-liquid extraction", "optb": "Solid-liquid extraction", "optc": "Multicomponent absorption with chemical reaction", "optd": "Multicomponent distillation.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following liquid-vapor contacting devices provides maximum contact surface area for a particular duty ?", "opta": "Sieve plate column", "optb": "Bubble cap column", "optc": "Randomly packed column", "optd": "Wetted wall column", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equipment frequently used for adiabatic humidification-cooling operation with recirculating liquid is", "opta": "natural draft cooling tower", "optb": "induced draft cooling tower", "optc": "spray chamber", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chemisorption (chemical adsorption) is", "opta": "same as \"Van der Waals\" adsorption.", "optb": "characterised by adsorption of heat.", "optc": "an irreversible phenomenon.", "optd": "a reversible phenomenon.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of solid-liquid extraction is limited by the", "opta": "phase change of the solute as it dissolves in the solvent.", "optb": "diffusion of the solute through the solvent in the pores to the outside of the particle.", "optc": "diffusion of the solute from the solution in contact with the particle to the main bulk of the solution.", "optd": "all 'a', 'b' & 'c'.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Raoult's law applies to the", "opta": "all liquid solutions", "optb": "non-ideal solution only.", "optc": "non-volatile solute.", "optd": "solvents.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In distillation columns, the number of bubble caps per tray primarily depends upon the", "opta": "allowable liquid velocity.", "optb": "allowable gas velocity.", "optc": "allowable gas and liquid velocities.", "optd": "feed composition.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In distillation, overhead product contains", "opta": "only one component", "optb": "two components", "optc": "any number of components", "optd": "only saturated liquid", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in pressure, the relative volatility for a binary system", "opta": "increases.", "optb": "decreases.", "optc": "remains same.", "optd": "either (a) or (b), depends on the system.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Low viscosity absorbent is preferred for reasons of", "opta": "rapid absorption rates and good heat transfer characteristics.", "optb": "improved flooding characteristics.", "optc": "low pressure drop on pumping.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mass transfer co-efficient (K) and diffusivity (D) are related according to film theory as", "opta": "K \u221d D", "optb": "K  \u221dD", "optc": "K  \u221d D1.5", "optd": "K  \u221d D2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}